<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Neil Fitzgerald on ...</title>
  <subtitle>Quality, Testing, Software Development, Photography, and more</subtitle>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-04-06T09:59:46.000Z</updated>
  <id>https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Neil Fitzgerald</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Requirements are Never Complete</title>
    <link href="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/2017/04/06/Requirements-are-Never-Complete/"/>
    <id>https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/2017/04/06/Requirements-are-Never-Complete/</id>
    <published>2017-04-06T10:57:25.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-04-06T09:59:46.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Requirements for software of any complexity, are never complete. There are always unstated assumptions, edge cases, and ambiguities that will remain. <a id="more"></a> Time does not stand still, and things change. New requirements and rules emerge in the usual business of developing software and feedback from the users. </p>
<p>See my post on <a href="/2017/04/06/Document-to-the-Right-Level">Document to the Right Level</a> for more about thinking about how much to document.</p>
<p>Different strategies are appropriate depending on circumstances to learn more and to make decisions about requirements. Develop good judgement as to when to apply a strategy.</p>
<h2 id="Common-Strategies"><a href="#Common-Strategies" class="headerlink" title="Common Strategies"></a>Common Strategies</h2><ul>
<li>Make a judgement call<ul>
<li>Sometimes just making a call as to how things should behave is appropriate.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Refer to standards<ul>
<li>Standards can provide good guidance on decision making. That standard can be one that has evolved specifically for that project, or an external one.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Talk to stakeholders<ul>
<li>Often there is a product owner who has deep knowledge of the users and the problem space. If there are cost implications in terms of time to implement, and maintainability, be sure to flag those to the stakeholders. Sometimes a less complete, or less elegant solution, will be the choice due to the costs of the more complex solution.</li>
<li>Be sure you know who the important stakeholders are that you need buy in from.</li>
<li>Learn the level of detail stakeholders want to be engaged at.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Refer to similar solutions<ul>
<li>Competing or similar solutions may have set user expectations for how a feature should behave. This can be a good proxy to talking to actual users.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Talk to users<ul>
<li>Finding out what your users actually need and want by talking to them is often an effective method, but can be relatively expensive. Some interpretation is needed. Users often can’t state their feedback in a way that can be directly applied to a particular question.  </li>
<li>User feedback is most useful for incremental changes.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Test user alternatives<ul>
<li>Testing alternative by putting them in front of real users is the ultimate check on the benefit and usability of alternatives. </li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Resources"><a href="#Resources" class="headerlink" title="Resources"></a>Resources</h2><ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Requirements_elicitation" target="_blank" rel="external">Requirements elicitation</a>. (n.d.). In Wikipedia.  </li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_requirements" target="_blank" rel="external">Software requirements</a>. (n.d.). In Wikipedia.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.mitre.org/publications/systems-engineering-guide/se-lifecycle-building-blocks/requirements-engineering/eliciting-collecting-and-developing-requirements" target="_blank" rel="external">Eliciting, Collecting, and Developing Requirements</a>. (2014). Mitre. In Systems Engineering Guide. </li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;Requirements for software of any complexity, are never complete. There are always unstated assumptions, edge cases, and ambiguities that will remain.
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="On Documentation" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/On-Documentation/"/>
    
      <category term="Documentation" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Documentation/"/>
    
      <category term="Requirements" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Requirements/"/>
    
      <category term="Process" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Process/"/>
    
      <category term="Software Development Lifecycle" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Software-Development-Lifecycle/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Document to the Right Level</title>
    <link href="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/2017/04/06/Document-to-the-Right-Level/"/>
    <id>https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/2017/04/06/Document-to-the-Right-Level/</id>
    <published>2017-04-06T10:54:27.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-04-06T09:54:27.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Documentation of functionality or test cases is always imperfect. The trick is to do enough to serve your needs, and not waste effort on documentation that will never be used. <a id="more"></a> Specifications and requirements have a way of changing and getting out of date, that quickly makes them obsolete. The effort to go back and keep them up to date needs to be weighed against the benefit of moving on to the next thing. </p>
<p>Documenting what testing should be done, and what was done is an area that should be adjusted to the situation. Who is doing the testing? If you are outsourcing testing to unknown contractors, who have little familiarity with your application, you will need to document test cases in exquisite detail. If you are using a small team, of dedicated testers who quickly become experts in the application, the level of documentation can be much more high level. </p>
<p>What are the stakes involved in the software? Software that deals with financial, medical, nuclear situations will require much more rigorous process and documentation. Most businesses, can do with much less as speed of delivery is more important.</p>
<p>How complex is a specific piece of functionality? If it needs to operate by a set of complex rules and algorithms, than more documentation is warranted. If you are essentially cloning existing simple functionality, a simple reference to that maybe sufficient.</p>
<p>How large is your team? The bigger the team, the more will need to be documented to facilitate keeping the team on the same page.</p>
<p>For features, is there enough detail to implement as described? Can a developer quickly clarify any ambiguity? Does a developer have the authority to make decisions when there is ambiguity? Is there enough detail for a tester, to know what to test, and what is important?</p>
<p>When a developer is handing off a feature to be tested by others, is there enough information to know what and how to test? If the developer already tested some aspects of the feature, on specific platforms, is that communicated so that testers can focus on areas that might have been missed?</p>
<p>As you situation changes, you will need to adjust your level of detail to that required by the situation. Be aware of your own leanings of over or under documenting.</p>
<h2 id="Key-Point"><a href="#Key-Point" class="headerlink" title="Key Point"></a>Key Point</h2><ul>
<li>Use good judgement on how much time to invest in documentation. Cost in time must be weighed with other priorities, and the benefit of having the documentation.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Resources"><a href="#Resources" class="headerlink" title="Resources"></a>Resources</h2><ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_documentation" target="_blank" rel="external">Software documentation</a>. (n.d.). In Wikipedia.    </li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;Documentation of functionality or test cases is always imperfect. The trick is to do enough to serve your needs, and not waste effort on documentation that will never be used.
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="On Documentation" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/On-Documentation/"/>
    
      <category term="Documentation" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Documentation/"/>
    
      <category term="Requirements" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Requirements/"/>
    
      <category term="Process" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Process/"/>
    
      <category term="Software Development Lifecycle" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Software-Development-Lifecycle/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Learn to Take Multiple Perspectives</title>
    <link href="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/2017/04/05/Learn-to-Take-Multiple-Perspectives/"/>
    <id>https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/2017/04/05/Learn-to-Take-Multiple-Perspectives/</id>
    <published>2017-04-05T13:07:40.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-04-05T12:07:40.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Expand your effectiveness by learning to take multiple perspectives. This expands the number of possible solutions and options you have. <a id="more"></a>In testing, it will allow you to generate more test cases and possible ways to find problems. When problem solving it can open up new paths to different solutions.</p>
<p>For example, with software testing, one of the basic skills is to be able to generate a list of things to test (test cases). Most people can look at the straight forward functionality presented and figure out combinations of things to test based on the spelled out functionality. If you start looking at it from other angles you can find more. </p>
<p>From a technological perspective what technologies were used? For example knowing that it is a web application backed by a SQL database, that uses HTML and JavaScript on the front end opens up a set of things that could have been overlooked. If you put SQL into text entry fields does it get processes (SQL Injection). If you put characters that have special meaning in HTML into your text inputs, are they handled appropriately?</p>
<p>From a business perspective does the functionality fulfill the business needs of earning money at reasonable cost. If it costs money every time a particular service is called, or if you are not managing your machine instances in the cloud for cost, are you best serving your business? Do the features line up with marketing promises to customers? Are there competitors that you need to differentiate from, or match capabilities with? Will a feature make the business more likely to earn more or less money?</p>
<p>From the customer perspective, does the software allow you to accomplish the tasks you want to with the software? How hard it is to accomplish common tasks? What is going to annoy you? What is going to delight you?</p>
<p>From a psychological perspective, what people were involved in building the software? What are their blind spots? What mistakes do they tend to make? How do they approach problems?</p>
<p>There are more perspectives to take. By going deeper, beyond the first level of the obvious, you can more quickly identify problems, and consider additional solutions.</p>
<h2 id="Key-Point"><a href="#Key-Point" class="headerlink" title="Key Point"></a>Key Point</h2><ul>
<li>Being able to take multiple perspectives expands your effectiveness, by expanding the problem solving approaches available.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;Expand your effectiveness by learning to take multiple perspectives. This expands the number of possible solutions and options you have.
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="On Testing" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/On-Testing/"/>
    
      <category term="Testing" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Testing/"/>
    
      <category term="Test Case Generation" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Test-Case-Generation/"/>
    
      <category term="Quality" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Quality/"/>
    
      <category term="Perspective Taking" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Perspective-Taking/"/>
    
      <category term="Effectiveness" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Effectiveness/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Sweat the Details</title>
    <link href="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/2017/04/04/Sweat-the-Details/"/>
    <id>https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/2017/04/04/Sweat-the-Details/</id>
    <published>2017-04-04T12:25:20.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-04-04T11:35:14.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Repeatedly in my career, lack of attention to detail has lead to quality problems. As a result attention to details is one of the behaviors I pay a lot of attention to in developers.<a id="more"></a> </p>
<p>As with most things there is a spectrum, and some trade offs. One team I worked with had a wide spread of people on the spectrum of attention to detail. On one end was a developer who turned out lots of code, with little attention to detail. This developer had a 30% re-open rate for bugs / tickets (the highest rate on the team). I was always able to find a bunch of bugs in this person’s work whenever something was delivered. At the other end, their was a developer who turned out far less features, but was so careful that the re-open rate was 5%. It was always a struggle to find issues in this person’s work. Their is definitely a sweet spot between the two in terms of feature delivery in a timely manner, versus sufficient quality. That sweet spot is at different places depending on the context and goals of a project.</p>
<h2 id="Repeated-themes"><a href="#Repeated-themes" class="headerlink" title="Repeated themes"></a>Repeated themes</h2><p>A number of common themes come up with details being missed. Some of the often found repeated themes are:</p>
<ul>
<li>Not addressing key user interaction in specifications</li>
<li>Not getting clarification on ambiguous detail in a specification</li>
<li>Skipping over key sentences in specifications or requirements</li>
<li>Only paying attention to the “happy path” through a use case</li>
<li>Missing changes required in related functionality</li>
<li>Skipping quality process steps - testing your own work, automated static code analysis, or code reviews</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Key-Points"><a href="#Key-Points" class="headerlink" title="Key Points"></a>Key Points</h2><ul>
<li>Mistakes are commonly made in the details</li>
<li>The difference in good and great is often in the details</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Resources"><a href="#Resources" class="headerlink" title="Resources"></a>Resources</h2><ul>
<li><a href="http://bip.softwarejewel.com/featured/why-are-the-smaller-details-also-important-6601/" target="_blank" rel="external">Why are the smaller details also important?</a> (January 20, 2011). Stephen Nellas. In Business Is Pleasure.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2005-10-11/be-obsessive-about-details" target="_blank" rel="external">Be Obsessive About Details</a>. (October 12, 2005). Michael Levine. In Bloomberg.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.reference.com/world-view/important-pay-attention-detail-10f11724639cf846" target="_blank" rel="external">Why is it important to pay attention to detail?</a> (n.d.). In Reference.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;Repeatedly in my career, lack of attention to detail has lead to quality problems. As a result attention to details is one of the behaviors I pay a lot of attention to in developers.
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Process" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Process/"/>
    
      <category term="Quality" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Quality/"/>
    
      <category term="On Process" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/On-Process/"/>
    
      <category term="Detail" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Detail/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Mistakes get repeated</title>
    <link href="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/2017/04/02/Mistakes-get-repeated/"/>
    <id>https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/2017/04/02/Mistakes-get-repeated/</id>
    <published>2017-04-02T17:19:33.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-04-03T14:58:09.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the strategies I find myself returning to for testing is looking at the kinds of mistakes that are made. Often a pattern can be found. Individuals tend to make the same type of mistake over and over. <a id="more"></a>For groups, areas that are complex are repeatedly forgotten when the connection to the current change is not obvious. </p>
<p>There are many strategies to help counter this tendency to repeat mistakes. If the problem is common across the group a checklist can be very effective as a short term fix. If it’s particular to an individual, collaborating on a strategy that works for them often is effective.</p>
<p>It reflects on the maturity and experience of the developer on how open they are to feedback. A good developer is always looking to up their game. They will find ways change their process to reduce their errors. </p>
<p>The industry has already identified a number of of practices that can reduce errors, and have automated solutions. Unit testing and checking code coverage is one such practice. Static code analysis such as using a linter is another. Considering how a problem can be avoided by automating a process. </p>
<p>How software is designed can have a big impact on errors. Prefer designs that are simple, or require all parts to be properly updated for new functionality to be added.</p>
<h2 id="Key-Points"><a href="#Key-Points" class="headerlink" title="Key Points"></a>Key Points</h2><ul>
<li>Its human nature to make the same type of mistakes.</li>
<li>Being mindful about why a mistake happened can lead to process or behavior changes that reduce the likelihood of the same type of mistake in the future.</li>
<li>Some upfront thought to design, process, and tooling can help reduce mistakes during implementation and ongoing development.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Resources"><a href="#Resources" class="headerlink" title="Resources"></a>Resources</h2><ul>
<li><a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2016/02/why-mistakes-are-often-repeated/470778/" target="_blank" rel="external">Why Mistakes Are Often Repeated</a>. (February 25, 2016). Olga Khazan. In The Atlantic. Retrieved April 2, 2017.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/anger-in-the-age-entitlement/201410/how-we-make-the-same-mistakes-over-and-over" target="_blank" rel="external">How We Make the Same Mistakes Over and Over</a>. (October 31, 2011). Steven Stosny, Ph.D.<br>In Psychology Today. Retrieved April 2, 2017.</li>
<li><a href="http://wiki.c2.com/?WhyDoPeopleMakeSoManyMistakes" target="_blank" rel="external">Why Do People Make So Many Mistakes?</a> (n.d.). In Wiki. Retrieved April 2, 2017.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;One of the strategies I find myself returning to for testing is looking at the kinds of mistakes that are made. Often a pattern can be found. Individuals tend to make the same type of mistake over and over.
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Process" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Process/"/>
    
      <category term="Software Development Lifecycle" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Software-Development-Lifecycle/"/>
    
      <category term="Quality" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Quality/"/>
    
      <category term="On Process" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/On-Process/"/>
    
      <category term="Bugs" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Bugs/"/>
    
      <category term="Best Practices" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Best-Practices/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <link href="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/2017/04/02/Introduction/"/>
    <id>https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/2017/04/02/Introduction/</id>
    <published>2017-04-02T16:49:13.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-04-03T14:55:44.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hi, I’m Neil. I work at <a href="http://www.vistaprint.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">Vistaprint</a>. I spend most of my time writing software or tools to help test other software. </p>
<a id="more"></a>
<p>I’m not a great writer. I tend to have poor transitions and leave things out. I use too many big words and long sentences. I’m working on it.</p>
<p>I’ve worked in the software industry for over 20 years. I’ve been around the block a bit. During that time I’ve had enough experiences with testing, software quality, and management to develop some thoughts on these topics. I plan to focus this blog mostly on these topics.</p>
<p>I’m constantly having to learn new technologies, and will likely will include some stuff on that too.</p>
<p>I’m into photography, kayaking and travel, go see my G+ for more of that. I took the picture that is used as the background on the about page.</p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;Hi, I’m Neil. I work at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vistaprint.com/&quot;&gt;Vistaprint&lt;/a&gt;. I spend most of my time writing software or tools to help test other software. &lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Bio" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Bio/"/>
    
      <category term="Objective" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Objective/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Fit Process</title>
    <link href="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/2017/04/01/The-Fit-Process/"/>
    <id>https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/2017/04/01/The-Fit-Process/</id>
    <published>2017-04-01T22:14:30.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-04-03T14:58:09.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Early in my career I worked for a company that tried to adopt the ISO 9000 standard to drive the software development process. I was already working on a disaster project, with both poor design and implementation. Rather than help correct course on the project the attempt to adopt the standard added to the chaos. <a id="more"></a>Progress on the project was already crawling, ground to almost a halt. The sign-off process required by the standard significantly slowed decision making and getting things done. Reams of write once, read never paperwork was generated. When an ISO 9000 auditor was brought in, the project manager generated lots of post facto records simply to comply with the standard and pass the audit.</p>
<p>All the work to comply with the standard resulted in negative quality results. All the projects in the department were delayed in delivery, with negative to no increase in quality. The paper work requirements proved to be an excessive burden for the quality goals for the projects in our department. The incentives as setup for the audit and standard did not generate a virtuous cycle of improvement, rather it created incentives to circumvent the process and emphasised compliance with the process, rather than doing what was right to deliver the projects meeting the delivery and quality goals of the company.</p>
<p>More recently I have worked for companies that have adopted aspects of agile processes. In general, the more the process is attempted to be applied cookie cutter as described in its idealized form, the less successful it tended to be. Agile process tends to be more successful, when practices are adopted when they make sense for a project, and with flexibility to adjust and adapt the practices to fit the character, development, and goals of a team.</p>
<h2 id="Key-learnings-about-process"><a href="#Key-learnings-about-process" class="headerlink" title="Key learnings about process:"></a>Key learnings about process:</h2><ul>
<li>Don’t do process for processes sake. A process is there to serve a purpose, not to be the purpose.</li>
<li>Don’t lose the point of a process.<ul>
<li>If you don’t know the why of the process, you don’t know if it’s really needed.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Good process addresses and leverages human behavioral tendencies.<ul>
<li>Making the process the path of least resistance, it helps with adoption.</li>
<li>The longer the process and more complex the process the less likely people are to follow it.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Strive for tools that support the process.<ul>
<li>Make it easy</li>
<li>Make the process unnecessary</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Just enough process to herd the cats, but no more.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Resources"><a href="#Resources" class="headerlink" title="Resources"></a>Resources</h2><ul>
<li><a href="https://michaelochurch.wordpress.com/2015/06/06/why-agile-and-especially-scrum-are-terrible/" target="_blank" rel="external">Why “Agile” and especially Scrum are terrible.</a> (June 6, 2015). Michael O. Church. Retrieved April 1, 2017.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;Early in my career I worked for a company that tried to adopt the ISO 9000 standard to drive the software development process. I was already working on a disaster project, with both poor design and implementation. Rather than help correct course on the project the attempt to adopt the standard added to the chaos.
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="Process" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Process/"/>
    
      <category term="Software Development Lifecycle" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Software-Development-Lifecycle/"/>
    
      <category term="Quality" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Quality/"/>
    
      <category term="On Process" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/On-Process/"/>
    
      <category term="Management" scheme="https://neilfitzgerald.github.io/tags/Management/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
